בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ע"א Ayin Aleph 71.
We pick up about six lines before the end on ע' עמוד
ב' Ayin Amud Bet at the word נשתתק ואמרו לו נכתוב גט
לאשתך. nishtatek v'amru lo nichtov get l'ishtecha. So first we had a
fascinating discussion about delivering the גט get when the husband was not
in his right mind because even though the question is can you
represent the husband, he doesn't have to be conscious at the moment,
he could be asleep, but you have to represent, you cannot represent
him as a שליח shaliach if he is not considered to be
בגברא b'gavra of sound mind. And the question is what if it's
a state that can be corrected and so on. So that was
a really interesting and relevant question. Now the question is that okay
if something happened and he can't speak, he doesn't have to give
a verbal direction, you can ask him and he can nod and
if it seems clear that he's able to respond meaningfully and you
ask him yes and no questions and he answers correctly then you
can follow his instructions based on his nodding and indication. So that's
the case in the משנה: mishna: נשתתק ואמרו לו נכתוב גט לאשתך.
nishtatek v'amru lo nichtov get l'ishtecha. So the גמרא Gemara says ולחוש
דילמא שיטה דלאו לאו נקט, אינמי שיטה דהן הן נקט, v'lechosh d'lamma
shita d'lav lav naktay, inami shita d'hen hen naktay,
maybe he just got seized by a fit
of nodding his head or shaking his head and therefore if you
ask him all yes
questions and he just keeps on going like this, it doesn't prove
anything. It's like you know the old joke, the guy brings his
dog into the bar and says, "Look, I could teach my dog
how to talk." He says, "Hey, what's on top of a building?"
"Roof." "See, he said roof." "Let's
see the opposite of smooth." "Rough." "See, he said rough." "Who's the
world's greatest baseball player?" "Ruth." "See, he said Babe Ruth." So the
guy's like, "You guys are crazy," throws him out of the bar,
the dog looks at his master and says, "Maybe I should have
said DiMaggio?" Okay.
All right, so anyway,
maybe he just started with this fit of nodding his head and
it happened to be right. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב
פפא דאמרינן ליה בסירוגין. amar Rav Papa d'amrinan leih b'sirugin.
So we ask him, we alternate between yes and no questions. I
mean that's not how רש"י Rashi reads it, but that's how I'm
going to read it. We alternate, well I don't know you can
look at רש"י, Rashi, he alternates between yes and no questions. So
the גמרא Gemara says, רש"י Rashi says you read it after waiting
a while, you wait an hour between the questions. That's רש"י. Rashi.
But I think it's more meaningful that the גמרא Gemara says let's
alternate. So the גמרא Gemara says ולחוש דילמא שיטה דסירוגין נקט, v'lechosh
d'lamma shita d'sirugin naktay, okay but maybe he's got this fit
of alternating between shaking his head and nodding his head. So the
גמרא Gemara says דאמרינן ליה חד לאו ותרי הן, ותרי לאו וחד
הן. d'amrinan leih chad lav u'trei hen, u'trei lav u'chad hen. So
we say like first ask him one no question and then two
yes questions and then two no questions and then one yes, whatever
it is, and one yes. So we mix it up, we don't
do a predictable order. Okay. דבי ר' ישמעאל תנא: D'vei Rishmael tana:
אמרינן ליה דברים של ימות החמה בימות הגשמים ושל ימות הגשמים בימות
החמה. amrinan leih devarim shel yemos hachama b'yemos hageshamim v'shel yemos hageshamim
b'yemos hachama. Now this seems to be a new point, like the
way we ask him questions. You ask him things relating to the
summer in the winter and in the winter in the summer. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי ניהו, mai nahu, what is that?
אילימא גלופקי וסדיני, ilema glufki v'sadini, if it's a winter coat and
a summer coat like you say do you want a winter coat
and do you want a summer coat and it's the wrong season,
ולחוש דילמא קורא
אחדיה, אינמי חמא אחדיה, v'lechosh d'lamma kora achteih, inami chama achteih, maybe
it's the summer but he's cold or maybe it's the winter but
he's hot, that doesn't prove anything. אלא בפירי, ela b'peiri, you ask
him about fruit. Do you want summer fruit or winter fruit? Now
תוספות Tosafot says you first of all you know but I don't
know תוספות Tosafot says sometimes you can preserve winter fruit in the
summer. Nowadays it's crazy that we can get fruit out of season.
So תוספות Tosafot says no, so what you say to him is
should we go to the orchards and pick pick you some apples
and you say that to him in the middle of the winter
or something like that. All right, anyway, moving on. I don't know
if anyone's writing because otherwise right, a lot of people were not
literate, I mean were not literate and were not able to write.
So yeah, I mean if he could write sure, totally, if he
could write of course. Okay, אמר רב כהנא אמר רב. amar Rav
Kahana amar Rav. Now speaking about writing, now we're going to have
a very important חידוש chiddush both in terms of a formal way
of defining things and also in terms of a very practical application
for how deaf people are categorized in הלכה. halacha. So חרש שיכול
לדבר מתוך הכתב, cheresh she'yachol l'daber mitoch haksav, if somebody who's deaf
but he can speak through writing. Now what do you mean deaf
can speak? Deaf is only deaf, but the point is that the
standard חרש cheresh in the גמרא Gemara means a deaf-mute, somebody who's
both deaf and can't speak. Now that does not what again I
think I've shared this with
you before when I was young and learned the גמרא Gemara I
said okay how many deaf people are both deaf and mute, but
the point is the גמרא Gemara presumed that most deaf people who
were born deaf were treated as mutes because they could not speak
intelligibly. So it doesn't mean that no nothing came out and in
an unintelligible way, which meant that people who were born deaf wound
up being defined
as
not בני דעה. bnei de'ah. status, you
know, he's an adult in הלכה Halakha and he can marry, do
מצוות, mitzvos, do all the types of acts that adults can do.
Okay? דאורייתא. De-oraissa. So that's it. Now, you could explain that in
one of two ways. You could either say that in a formalistic
way, writing, you know, writing is considered an act of speech, and
that's the language that רב כהנא אמר רב Rav Kahana Amar Rav
uses. יכול לדבר מתוך הכתב. Yakhol ledaber mitokh haksav. Can speak through
writing. So let's just say he's not mute, he speaks. He speaks
through writing, which is going to be obviously very relevant when deaf
people learn sign language, right? And does that become a form of
they're no longer they're able to speak? Or you could just say,
no, the question with a deaf person is, is that we think
he doesn't have דעת, daas, and here we clearly have an indicator
that he clearly does have דעת, daas, so that redefines him. Okay,
but it seems some well, the difference would be, well we'll see,
the difference would be that if we need to satisfy a formal
definition and it's not enough to test for דעת, daas, then you
could say that it's a very rigid formal definition. Okay. So then
anyway, but it sounds like we're saying that this qualifies him as
an act of speech. שראוי שיכול לדבר מתוך הכתב כותבין ונותנין גט
לאשתו. She-rauy she-yakhol ledaber mitokh haksav, kosvin venosin get le-ishto. So you
can write a גט get to his wife, even a woman that
he married when he was not a חרש, cheresh, right? If he
married this woman only as a חרש, cheresh, it's not קידושין דאורייתא.
kiddushin de-oraissa. So the גמרא Gemara says before, and it'll say again,
כשם שכונס ברמיזה כך מוציא ברמיזה. keshem she-kones bi-remiza, kach motzi bi-remiza.
Right? The same way he married a woman through just signaling, and
with that, you know, and it was only a rabbinic marriage, he
can divorce her in the same way. But here we're assuming he
married her when he was a פיקח, pikeach, and then he became
deaf-mute after. Okay, so therefore he's דאורייתא de-oraissa married to this woman.
Nevertheless, says רב כהנא אמר רב, Rav Kahana Amar Rav, if he
can speak through writing, he's considered a בר דעת bar daas and
he can divorce this woman. And we can write a גט get
for his wife. So
אמר רב יוסף מאי קמשמע לן? amar Rav Yosef, mai kamashma lan?
Now רב יוסף Rav Yosef takes it as like, oh, this is
obvious. Okay, תנינא, tanina, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, נשתתק, nishtatek,
if somebody is silent, ואמרו לו נכתב גט לאשתך והרכין בראשו, ve-amru
lo niktav get le-ishtecha, ve-irkin berosho, and we say to him to
write a גט get and he nodded his head, בודקין אותו שלש
פעמים, bodkin oso shalosh pe'amim, I check him three times, אם אמר
על לאו לאו ועל הן הן, im amar al lav lav veal
hein hein, if he says yes correctly and no correctly, הרי אלו
יכתבו ויתנו, harei elu yichtevu ve-yitnu, they can write it and give
it. So obviously you don't need to have a
verbal instruction. Now the point is, that this is a much bigger
חידוש chiddush than that. He says, אמר ליה רב זירא, amar leih
Rav Zeira, wait a minute, the משנה Mishnah is talking about just
a guy that's mute, that can't speak. שאני אלם דתניא, shani ilem
de-tanya, אלם ilem is different, אלם ilem of course is a בר
דעת. bar daas. There the only question was did it constitute legitimate
instruction, you know, from the husband. Because שאני אלם דתניא, shani ilem
de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, מדבר ואינו שומע זהו חרש,
medaber ve-eino shomea zehu cheresh, somebody who can speak and not hear,
that's termed as a
חרש. cheresh. שומע ואינו מדבר זהו אלם, shomea ve-eino medaber zehu ilem,
somebody can hear and not speak,
that's considered mute. וזה וזה הרי הן כפיקחין לכל דבריהם. ve-ze ve-ze
harei hen kepikechin lekhol divreihen. And somebody who's only just deaf or
just mute is considered fully to be of right mind and of
a capacity and so on. Okay, now what? Like כפיקחין. kepikechin. Yeah,
with the כ, kaph, כפיקחין. kepikechin. Yeah, but פיקח, pikeach,
yeah, that's true. Anyway, וממאי דמדבר ואינו שומע זהו חרש שומע ואינו
מדבר זהו אלם, umimai de-medaber ve-eino shomea zehu cheresh, shomea ve-eino medaber
zehu ilem, how do you know that those are the terms that
we use for them? It's so funny, like it doesn't ask that
about any other term that's used in whatever, but fine. דכתיב, de-chitiv,
it says, ואני כחרש לא אשמע, va'ani kacheresh lo eshma,
I like was a mute person, I was that did not hear,
that person did not hear, וכאלם לא יפתח פיו, ukhe'ilem lo yiftach
piv, and like a mute person who did not open his mouth.
ואיתימא, ve-itayma, or if you want, כדאמרי אינשי, kide'amri inshi, אשתתק מלוליה,
ishtatek miluleih,
so as a sort of ראשי תיבות rashei teivos of אלם, ilem,
אשתתק מלוליה, ishtatek miluleih,
his words have been taken away. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara basically
says, of course it's a חידוש, chiddush, right? All the משנה Mishnah
teaches you, if somebody who's a בר דעת bar daas who can't
speak does not need to give verbal instruction to write a גט,
get, if you can test that he is able to signal properly,
then it does not have to be verbal instruction. The חידוש chiddush
of רב כהנא אמר רב Rav Kahana Amar Rav is somebody that
normally we categorize as an אינו בר דעת, eino bar daas, as
a חרש, cheresh, and somebody who normally we say does not have
the intellectual capacity, cannot be obligated in מצוות mitzvot and so on,
cannot do halakhic transactions, that person who's able to write, that's considered
that he's no longer a חרש. cheresh. That's a huge חידוש. chiddush.
Okay. Now the point is, I'm just not to ruin the end
result, but I want to say, if the גמרא Gemara were to
end here, there never would have been a halakhic question. about mute
people who are able to communicate by sign language, right? Because I
mean, you know, because it's יכול לדבר, yachol ledaber, יכול לדבר מתוך
היד, yachol ledaber mitoch hayad, יכול לדבר מתוך הכתב. yachol ledaber mitoch
haksav. Certainly if they were able to write, right, end of story,
they're no longer a חרש. cheresh. But just to warn you, the
גמרא Gemara is not going to end like that. Okay, that's the
חידוש chiddush of רב כהנא אמורא, Rav Kahana Amora, but we're not
going to be left with that at the end. Okay, so that
is a very big חידוש. chiddush. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, says רב זירא, Rav
Zeira, אי קשיא לי הא קשיא לי. ee kashya lee ha kashya
lee. If I have a question, here's my question.
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, אם לא יגיד ונשא
עוונו. im lo yagid venasa avono. So this is a point that
if somebody is called to testify and you say, okay, and you
have testimony to bring to me in court, and he says, "No,
I don't," and you say, "Swear to me that you don't have
testimony that you can bring to support my case," and he takes
an oath and he's lying, then if he לא יגיד, lo yagid,
if he does not give his testimony, he bears his sin and
then he has to basically bring a קרבן, korban, a special קרבן,
korban, okay, שבועה shvua for the false oath. So here we're saying,
so from here we can also learn some of the laws that
relate to עדות eidus because it speaks about what it would mean
for that person to testify. A falsehood of omission, as it were.
Right, but he's took an oath. He falsely he omitted the עדות,
eidus, but he was commission of falsely swearing. Okay, אם לא יגיד,
im lo yagid, if he does not give his testimony, פרט לאלם
שאינו יכול להגיד. perat le-illem she-eino yachol lehagid. So if somebody is
mute and cannot speak, I don't know exactly how he takes an
oath, that's interesting. Can you take an oath without verbally enunciating? Anyway,
but anyway, then he does not have to, then he is exempt,
then he is exempt from the קרבן שבועה korban shvua and similarly
presumably he can't, I mean the more basic the first basic point
is he can't testify, because testimony has to be verbal. That's the
point of this, what we learn out from this פסוק. pasuk. I
mean it doesn't say in the פסוק, pasuk, but יגיד yagid to
relate, where we חז"ל Chazal understand mean to relate verbally. אמאי, Amai,
now according to you, רב כהנא אמורא, Rav Kahana Amora, that writing
is a form of speaking, right, that's basically what they're saying, writing
is a form of speaking, so why is this person excluded from
testifying? היכול להגיד מתוך הכתב. hayachol lehagid mitoch haksav. And now by
the way, Michael, you see the answer to your other question, why
it matters to say that this is, they're not just saying a
test for intellect, they're saying הלכתית halakhically writing is defined as speaking.
Well if that's true, then for, you know, עדות eidus makes no
difference? Okay, but if you basically start by a definitional point, writing
is a form of speaking, speaking through writing, then that could be
applied to a wide range of הלכות. halakhot. So the גמרא Gemara
says if that's true, why can't that be a, why can't you
testify through writing? So the גמרא Gemara says,
היכול להגיד. hayachol lehagid. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, עדות קאמרת?
eidus ka-amrat? What, you're talking about testimony? Like Michael said, שאני עדות
דרחמנא אמר מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם. shani eidus derachmana amar mipihem velo
mipi ksavam. עדות eidus is a special higher requirement. It says על
פי שנים עדים. al pi shenayim eidim. It has to be through
their mouth and not through their writing. And therefore, even if in
general that's considered speaking, it's not considered verbal speaking, it's not considered
מפיהם. mipihem. So if the תורה Torah says על פי, al pi,
then it has to be verbal speech. But otherwise, writing would be
a form of talking or speaking and it would work for חרש
cheresh and maybe work for other הלכות halakhot as well. So according
to that, להגיד lehagid could be דרך כתיבה. derech ketiva. להגיד lehagid
could, but we also had a פסוק pasuk that says מפי, mipi,
and that was and that excluded this case. Okay, so now we're
still working that writing is a form of speaking. By the way,
parenthetically,
תוספות Tosafot in other גמרות Gemorot discuss a very interesting question about
whether you can take a, what's it called, a deposition, right, whether
somebody who cannot come up come to court to testify, whether they
can give their testimony through writing. Or actually what תוספות Tosafot speaks
about is not that some lawyers come and sit down and he
gives his testimony to them, but he basically like writes a letter
and sends in his testimony to court. And that seems to be
a problem about מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם, mipihem velo mipi ksavam, right,
it certainly does seem to be that problem. But תוספות Tosafot has
an interesting discussion of ways to limit this restriction to allow for
that case to take place, because you could obviously imagine the difficulty,
right, about bringing, getting people to come or to travel and so
on. On the other hand, if you can't cross-examine the witness, you
know, it also has other problems. So anyway, but I just wanted
to mention that that was a practical issue that תוספות Tosafot and
the ראשונים Rishonim discussed. But it's even מפיהם mipihem that they can
physically enunciate words. If they're talking in a language you don't understand,
they also wouldn't be allowed. Right, so that's an excellent point as
well. But it has to be מפיהם ולא מפי המתורגמן. mipihem velo
mipi hameturgeman. Right, and you know, בית דין Beis Din had to
know שבעים לשון, shivim lashon, so they, because you can't get somebody
to stand between the the person testifying and hearing, because, you know,
critical information could be lost. Yeah, way I believe רש"י Rashi says
that the way in which you impose the שבועה shvua is again
by his just nodding his head. Oh, did I miss that? אם
לא יגיד והוא עד או ראה או ידע. im lo yagid vehu
ed o ra'ah o yada. Oh, you're right, רש"י Rashi addressed it.
Thank you. Right, right. So that's, but that what I guess work
as a as a type of שומע כעונה shome'a k'oneh type of
a thing, but that's excellent point. Right. So there you go, because
it might have to be verbal, but you... provided the verbal and
he nodded, so that counts as the קבלה. kabbalah. Thank you, I
missed that רש"י. Rashi. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So
we're still making that argument that writing is a form of speaking,
and with the exception of עדות, edus, and that would work for
חרש. cheresh. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this: כשם שבודקין אותו
לגיטין, keshem shebodkin oso l'gittin,
this is the guy who was to no longer speak, thank you,
and you test him by asking these questions and he nods etc.
So the same way this guy the nodding works, not a חרש,
cheresh, the nodding of the guy who can't speak for גט get
purposes, כך בודקין אותו למשא ומתנות, kach bodkin oso l'massa u'mattanot,
you can test him for exchanges, meaning buying and selling, like, you
know, some guy's
business transactions, something happens he can't speak, so he can, you know,
he can signal, that's fine, and you use that, if you use
it as good enough indicator of דעת da'as for גט, get, you
can use it obviously for other things, ולאדעיות u'l'eduyos and for testimony,
ולירושות u'l'yerushos and for bequests, קתני מיהא אדעיות, katani miha eduyos, so
now we've got a problem, right? You said that עדות edus requires
verbal, here it's clear עדות edus does not require verbal. אמר רב
יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi amar
Rav Sheshet, בעדות אשה דהקילו בה רבנן, b'edus isha d'hikilu bah rabbanan,
no, that's testifying that a woman's husband is dead, there obviously we
have really lowered the standards, but classic testimony would have to be
verbal. והקתני ירושות, v'ha'katani yerushos,
but doesn't it also say bequests? Presumably means he's testifying regarding a
bequest that somebody made or that somebody died in purpose of that
the heirs now can inherit? אמר רבי אבהו ירושות בנכור, Amar Rabi
Abahu yerushos b'nichor,
so what it means is that he's testifying which of his sons
is the firstborn or that a son that people thought was the
firstborn wasn't really the firstborn. Okay, so that's again not a formal
act of עדות edus and that's why that works. קתני מיהא משא
ומתנות, Katani miha massa u'mattanot, but it also says regarding business transactions,
מאי לאו לעלמא, mai lav l'alma, doesn't it mean
he can testify about other people's business transactions? I don't know if
I would say that would be פשט, pshat, לא בדידיה, lo b'didia,
no, it means he can engage in his own business transactions. Okay,
so anyway, that was a ברייתא braisa that seemed to say you
don't need to be verbal speech for עדות edus and the גמרא
Gemara says no, you do still need it for עדות. edus. Okay,
but we're still back to the main חידוש chiddush of רב כהנא
אמר רב Rav Kahana amar Rav that a חרש cheresh who can
write is not considered a חרש. cheresh. So now the גמרא Gemara
goes, it's a form of speaking. מיתיבי, Meitivei, says the גמרא, Gemara,
I'll ask you on this:
חרש, Cheresh, the חרש cheresh who's the deaf mute, who's not a
בר דעת bar da'as הלכתית, hilchasit, והלכו בו אחר רמיזותיו ואחר קפיצותיו
ואחר כתב ידו, v'halchu bo achar remizosav v'achar k'fitzosav v'achar k'sav yado,
the חז"ל Chazal did not follow his, you know, signaling through his
like hand or his jumping up and down as a way of
indicating, or even his
writing, אלא במטלטלין, ella b'mitaltelin, only when it comes to transactions of
chattel, which we have a lower standard. You might remember that we
even allowed like kids of the age of six or seven to
engage in those types of transactions, אבל לא לגיטין, aval lo l'gittin,
not for the purpose of a גט. get. Okay, so if he's
דאורייתא d'oraisa married, if he's only דרבנן d'rabbanan married it's a different
story, if he was married as a חרש cheresh he could be
divorced as a חרש, cheresh, but if he was married as a
non-חרש, cheresh, this will not work for דאורייתא d'oraisa purposes of גט.
get. So this is against רב כהנא אמר רב, Rav Kahana amar
Rav, writing does not constitute an act of speaking. So the גמרא
Gemara says אה, ah, isn't this a contradiction? So the גמרא Gemara
says תנאי היא, tanna'ei hi, it's a debate of תנאים, tannaim, דתניא,
d'tanya, we turned a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, במה דברים אמורים בחרש מעיקרו, bameh devarim amorim
b'cheresh mei'ikaro,
when is this true that somebody cannot write a גט get for
his wife, I mean, you know, signal to have a גט get
for his wife? If he was always a חרש. cheresh. Now, Michael's
jumping in and saying I've been telling you since the beginning of
the דף daf today that if he married the woman as a
חרש cheresh he can divorce her as a חרש. cheresh. So what's
going on here? So the גמרא's Gemara going to deal with it.
I'll just tell you the answer. The answer the גמרא's Gemara going
to do is there's one way a חרש cheresh who was always
a חרש cheresh who was always a חרש cheresh could be married
to a woman דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Now a חרשת chereshet you can figure
out, her father married her, but how about if the guy's a
חרש? cheresh? So the answer is, remember יבום? yibbum? יבום yibbum we
always get revisited with יבום, yibbum, okay? So anyway, so it was
like when we learned קדשים, kodashim, you couldn't get away from ילה.
ilah. So when you learned נשים, nashim, not מילה milah excuse me,
well yeah, what was it that kept coming back by קדשים? kodashim?
No, no, it wasn't מילה, milah, it was פיגול. pigul. You couldn't
get away with פיגול. pigul. Anyway, so with נשים nashim you can't
get away from יבום. yibbum. Anyway, so we're going to see that
if his brother died and the act of יבום yibbum is created
just through the act of sex even without דעת, da'as, right? So
therefore, a חרש cheresh who has sex with his sister-in-law after the
brother die would be married to her דאורייתא d'oraisa as יבום. yibbum.
Okay, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. So the
גמרא's Gemara going to say if he was always a חרש cheresh
then he never was
established. He was always a חרש. cheresh. Then his ability to write
does not redefine him. Okay, אבל פקח ונתחרש, aval pikeach venischaraish, somebody
who was once well, once hearing, and then became deaf, okay? So
it's considered to be that that person maybe we are more prepared
to assume that he could be a בר דעת, bar daas, or
you know, he established himself once as that. So in that case,
הוא כותב והן חותמין. hu kosev vehein chosmin. Then if he writes,
that will be sufficient and then other people can sign onto his
גט. get. So there is a here distinction that we're more prepared
to recategorize somebody who once was a, you know, a non-חרש, cheresh,
somebody who was once hearing, as opposed to somebody who always was
a חרש, cheresh, we are not going to recategorize. Now that's רבן
גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. והחכמים Ve-hachachamim don't even make that distinction at all.
So what we have is, we have this great approach of רב
כהנא ורב, Rav Kahana ve-Rav, which would have been terrific in terms
of עגונות, agunios, the הלכה halachic history of defining the הלכה halachic
status of deaf people, but the גמרא Gemara now has shown a
ברייתא braisa that goes against it. And now what we're left with
is either a complete rejection of רב כהנא ורב, Rav Kahana ve-Rav,
that writing never redefines, or if it redefines, at most only for
a person who started life not as a חרש. cheresh. That's רבן
גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. Okay, but if somebody started life as a חרש,
cheresh, then we completely reject that position. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like
this. בחרש שהוא לא חרש מעיקרא? becheresh shehu lo cheresh me-ikara? Ostensibly,
ostensibly can speak or this is a person who can't speak? No,
somehow he was like, now he also can't speak. Right, he also
can't speak. Now there could have been some illness or something. Okay,
one also wonders, right, let's say this change happened before he was
בר מצווה bar mitzvah or she was בת מצווה, bas mitzvah, right?
Is it because הלכה halachically you had achieved, he had achieved the
status of a בר דעת? bar daas? Is it a formal idea?
So that status is easier to restore as it were? Or is
it just the fact that somehow, no, because they began life with
those capacities, then somehow we assume that they're, I don't know, that
they have more capacities even when they're less, you know, clearly evident
or something. It's not exactly clear why the גמרא Gemara assumes that
there's, it's easier to redefine somebody who was once a, once you
know, once a פקח, pikeach, yeah. And as a matter of הלכה
halachic method, so they, the ancients have no concept, I don't think,
of a sign language as a full language with a grammar. Right,
that they certainly did not. But כתב, ksav, they had כתב! ksav!
So that's the הלכה halachic challenge, is that if the גמרא Gemara
already says that somebody who could write intelligibly, where it's precise communication,
clear indication of intelligence, and the גמרא's Gemara going to say that
that person, even though they were born a חרש, cheresh, is not
הלכה halachically a בר דעת, bar daas, right? Obviously you see that
that presents a challenge to redefine even once you have schools for
the deaf and sign language and the whole thing, right?
Unless we read it so formalistically, because that's what the גמרא Gemara
says, this guy was born a חרש, cheresh, he's communicating through writing,
and he's still a חרש, cheresh, right? If somebody's communicating through writing,
they're communicating precisely, they are whatever. So yeah, I so you know,
so it's interesting because this is exactly where הלכה halacha essentially
למעשה, lema'aseh, there are many many פוסקים poskim that say nowadays a
חרש cheresh who can communicate through sign language or whatever is not
a חרש. cheresh. End of story. Okay? And obviously that's a very
logical position, besides it being sensitive and inclusive, it's a very logical
position you would want us to arrive at, right? You know, and
there are many פוסקים poskim who פסק pasken that way. I follow
that פסק psak as well, but I think we should just acknowledge
that it has to deal with the fact that the גמרא Gemara
has somebody communicating precisely through writing, right? Which clearly shows intelligence, clearly
is, you know, precise, articulate communication, and nevertheless still a חרש. cheresh.
So you have to deal with this גמרא. Gemara. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Question? Yeah? Correct me if I'm wrong, but don't we also
say that if there's a lady who got married, you know, not
through her father, whatever, like you married a חרשת, chereshes, right? Do
we make it, I thought, like, you know, more difficult to divorce
her because we're worried about like, she'll be abused by other... a
little bit, that's true, if she's a you know, very... okay, well
we'll see, yes, it's true, but I don't want to get into
that. Okay, but we'll see a little bit of that anyway, fine.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, כשם שכונסה ברמיזה כך
מוציאה ברמיזה, kshem shekone-sa beremiza kach motzi-a beremiza, says the גמרא, Gemara,
I'm sorry, did I skip a line? אבל פקח ונתחרש הוא כותב
והן חותמין. aval pikeach venischaraish hu kosev vehein chosmin. וחרש מעיקרא לא?
vecheresh me-ikara lo? If someone was always a חרש cheresh he can't
divorce his wife? But don't we say דכשם שכונסה ברמיזה כך מוציאה
ברמיזה? de-kshem shekone-sa beremiza kach motzi-a beremiza? The same way he was
able to signal and indicate and we use that as a basis
for him to do a קידושין, kiddushin, so also if he signals
and indicates we'll write a גט get on his behalf. The whole
קידושין kiddushin was only רבנן rabbanan so the divorce could work as
well. So if he was always a חרש cheresh what's the problem?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, אי באשה הכי נמי. ee be-isha
hachi nami. If it was a woman he married then you're right,
he could divorce her. He married her as a חרש, cheresh, can
divorce her as a
חרש. cheresh. הכא במאי עסקינן? hacha bemai askinan? What are we talking
about? ביבמתו, beyivamto, that it was his sister-in-law and therefore even though
he was a חרש, cheresh, once he did an act and once
he had sex. sex with her, that created, that created a דאורייתא
d'oraisa marriage, okay, because for sex you don't need to be a
בר דעת. bar daas. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says now, יבמתו
ממאן, yevamto miman, who, you know, who was he through whom was
she his sister-in-law? Meaning who was his brother? אילימא דנפלה ליה מאחיו
חרש, eileima d'nafla lei mei'achiv chereish, if his brother himself was a
חרש, chereish, so כשם שכניסתה ברמיזה כך יציאתה ברמיזה. keshem shek'nisata b'remiza
kach yetziata b'remiza.
So if she was married to her brother as a rabbinic marriage
through the fact that he was a חרש, chereish, then even though
he did יבום, yibum, right, he only did, everything here is all
rabbinic. So he got her, the act of יבום yibum that now
makes him connected to her all was functioning on a rabbinic foundation,
right, because the whole initial marriage was rabbinic. What? Allowing rabbinic יבום?
yibum? Well because, because דאורייתא d'oraisa by the same virtue, דאורייתא d'oraisa
she's not his sister-in-law, right? So דאורייתא d'oraisa the marriage to the
brother wasn't binding and she's not his sister-in-law, and within the rabbinic
sort of construct that it was a marriage and she is his
sister-in-law, then there's יבום. yibum. But the whole thing is basically all
rabbinic. So he can still divorce her. It's fascinating that we would
privilege יבום yibum even in that case over a rabbinic חליצה. chalitza.
Right, that is, you know, but very astounding to me. I mean
it's an interesting question if we allow a rabbinic חליצה chalitza in
that case. When the her brother was a פיקח, pikeach, we don't
allow חליצה chalitza because he's not a בר דעת. bar daas. I
don't know in that case, in that case we might allow, I'd
have to check, we might allow. If we're going to allow a
rabbinic גט, get, we might as well allow a rabbinic חליצה, chalitza,
but I'd have to check. Okay, so אלא דנפלה ליה מאחיו פיקח.
ela d'nafla lei mei'achiv pikeach.
Now his brother was a non-חרש, chereish, דאורייתא d'oraisa married to the
brother. Now he has a דאורייתא d'oraisa obligation of יבום. yibum. But
they're married to the woman? What? דאורייתא d'oraisa married to the woman.
דאורייתא d'oraisa she was married to the brother, okay, she was married
to the brother דאורייתא, d'oraisa, the brother was a פיקח, pikeach, brother
died, now he has sex with her, דאורייתא d'oraisa it's יבום, yibum,
and now דאורייתא d'oraisa they're married, he can't divorce her. Okay. ואיבעית
אימא v'iba'is eima if he was a חרש מעיקרא, chereish mei'ikara, right?
If he was a חרש מעיקרא, chereish mei'ikara, according, right. ואיבעית אימא,
v'iba'is eima, if you want I could say לעולם דנפלה ליה מאחיו
חרש, l'olam d'nafla lei mei'achiv chereish, even in the case that his
brother was a חרש. chereish. You're right, it would all be rabbinic
in that case,
but גזירה אחיו חרש אטו אחיו פיקח. gzeira achiv chereish atu achiv
pikeach. But you know what, the same way we've established that if
the brother was a פיקח pikeach it would become a דאורייתא d'oraisa
marriage through יבום yibum and he could not give a גט, get,
so the same would be true if the brother was a חרש,
chereish, we would make a גזירה gzeira and say also in that
case of יבום yibum he can't give her, he can't give her
a גט. get. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ee hachi,
if that's true, so אשתו נמי. ishto nami. So if he married
the woman as a חרש, chereish, let's not let her give a
גט get because it will come to marry the woman as a
פיקח pikeach or whatever or something like that. So the גמרא Gemara
says no.
יבמתו ביבמתו מיחלפא. yevamto b'yevamto michalfa. It's two cases of a sister-in-law.
And he is always a חרש. chereish. Okay, so whether the sister-in-law
came to him through his brother who was a פיקח, pikeach, brother
was a חרש, chereish, that you still in your mind would categorize
that all as a sister-in-law case. It's not referring to the actor
himself. So that's the case where we could say you could confuse
them. And since one of them a גט get doesn't work, it
won't work in the other one. But אשתו ביבמתו לא מיחלפא. ishto
b'yevamto lo michalfa. If we allow him to give a גט get
to his wife if he married her as a חרש, chereish, that's
not going to be confused and say oh, so now I can
give a גט get to my sister-in-law. Okay, cat- we obviously put
wife and sister-in-law in different categories. Okay, so that's the argument. The
argument is that obviously as a wife he married as a חרש
chereish he can divorce as a חרש. chereish. Sister-in-law, if it came
through his brother who was a פיקח, pikeach, then he cannot divorce
her, and maybe even if it came through his brother who was
a חרש chereish can't divorce her because maybe we'll come to confuse
the two cases. But the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge that.
ומי גזרינן חרש אטו פיקח? umi gazrinan chereish atu pikeach? You know,
we're still, we're still digressing from the first basic point of רב
כהנא ורב, Rav Kahana v'Rav, we'll get back to it. Are we
really concerned that if we allow certain cases by a case of
sister-in-law of יבום yibum with a חרש chereish brother-in-law that will lead
to cases of a פיקח pikeach brother-in-law, we're afraid the יבום yibum
cases will get confused? והתנן, v'hatnan, and we taught in the משנה,
Mishna,
שני אחים חרשים, shnei achim charashim, if you have two brothers that
are both חרשים, charashim, okay, so then it doesn't matter, and this
is going to be a case of יבום yibum and one of
them is going to die. So it doesn't matter who the women
are that they married, the marriages will all be דרבנן d'rabbanan because
both of the both of the brothers are חרשים. charashim. נשואין שתי
אחיות פקחות, nesuin shtei achayot pikchot, they're married either to two and
they're married to two sisters, either these two sisters both are are
פיקחות, pikchot, they're not
חרש, chereish, או שתי חרשות, o shtei charashot, או שתי אחיות אחת
פיקחת ואחת חרשת, o shtei achayot achat pikechet v'achat chereshet, or or
one of each. Okay, doesn't matter in all those cases, it's only
קידושי דרבנן. kiddushei d'rabbanan. Now if it were קידושי דאורייתא, kiddushei d'oraisa,
okay, two brothers married to two sisters and one brother died, what
would the הלכה halacha be? And they're both חרש? chereish? No, normal
case, two every- everybody is פיקח. pikeach. You can't, because you married
your
sister- it would be a case of עריות, arayot, right? It would
be a case of... so you wouldn't have to do חליצה, chalitza,
right? If the sister-in-law is an ערוה. erva. from a different perspective,
because now it's your wife's sister, not just your sister-in-law, right? Then
you're—then no ייבום yibbum no חליצה. chalitza. So similarly, if we produce—reproduce
that at the rabbinic level, brothers and sisters and it's all rabbinic,
we could say, well we'll—we'll treat this off since it's all working
on the same plane, and no ייבום yibbum and no חליצה. chalitza.
The trick is going to be is if one of those marriages
is rabbinic and one is דאורייתא, de'oraita, right? If the חרש cheresh
is married to a woman rabbinically, and now he's got a ייבום
yibbum obligation with a woman that's his דאורייתא de'oraita sister-in-law. So that,
thankfully, we're not going to deal with that case. Okay, that's the
complicated case. We're establishing the cases that are easy, okay? וכן, vechen,
but that's the case that's complicated, because then he has a conflict
between his current marriage which is only rabbinic and his דאורייתא de'oraita
obligation of ייבום. yibbum. Okay, וכן שתי אחיות חרשות vechen shtei achayot
cherashot or if both of the women, sisters, are חרשות, cherashot, it
doesn't matter what the men are, it's all going to be rabbinic.
נשואות לשני אחים פקחים nisu'ot lishnei achim pikchim to the two brothers
who are both of, you know, well, not—not deaf-mute, או לשני אחים
חרשים o lishnei achim cherashim or two that are deaf-mute, או לשני
אחים אחד פקח ואחד חרש o lishnei achim echad pike'ach ve'echad cheresh
or one of each. Anyway in all those scenarios the—it's—we're all talking
about rabbinic marriage. Everything is rabbinic. So in that case, הרי אלו
פטורות מן החליצה ומן הייבום. harei elu peturot min hachalitza umin hayibbum.
So since they're all operating on the same plane, it's all rabbinic,
so we treat it as a case of ייבום yibbum with עריות,
arayot, and they're exempt from ייבום yibbum and חליצה. chalitza. Okay. ואם
היו נכריות יכנסו. ve'im hayu nochriyot yichnesu.
Now, if they were not sisters, if they were unrelated to one
another—it doesn't mean non-Jewish women—if they were—if they were strangers, if they
were unrelated to one another, so then you do ייבום. yibbum. Okay,
then it doesn't matter even if one marriage is דרבנן derabbanan and
one is דאורייתא, de'oraita, okay, then there's a—and then there's a
sister-in-law, there's a ייבום, yibbum, you do ייבום yibbum and there's not
עריות, arayot, your wife is not related to this other woman. Okay.
יכנסו. yichnesu. ואם רצו להוציא יוציאו. ve'im ratzu lehotzi yotzi'u. And if
now if they want—now again,
assuming that everything is rabbinic, if everything is rabbinic and the women
are not related to one another, you do ייבום. yibbum. Now, since
the ייבום yibbum was rabbinic, right? Because everything was rabbinic, everybody got
it? If both of the men—either both of the men or both
of the women are חרשות, cherashot, if everything is rabbinic and there's
not an עריות arayot case here, then you do—you can do ייבום
yibbum and after you've done ייבום, yibbum, you could also do גט.
get. Okay, because it was all rabbinic, so the same way the
ייבום yibbum made—made this woman his wife through—through, you know, rabbinically, he
can now divorce her rabbinically as well. Okay, everybody got the point
of this? Right, the simple point is, if everything is rabbinic, then
we work as if every—then we act as if it all is
working on a דאורייתא de'oraita plane. So if there's an עריות arayot
case you do nothing, if there's not an עריות arayot case they
can do ייבום, yibbum, but they can also then afterwards do a
גט get because the same way it works rabbinically to create it,
it can also be separated rabbinically as well. Yes. Could you just
go over why a חרש cheresh cannot divorce a biblical? Because he's
not considered a בר דעת. bar da'at. He's not considered to be
of full mind, full, you know, intellectual capacities. That's the rabbinic assumption.
And that means he cannot do any type of transaction that's recognized
at a דאורייתא de'oraita level. Yeah, so that's the big issue, right?
Because again, the—what that would be, the consequence of that is, you
have somebody now who's a deaf-mute who can, you know, highly intelligent
can communicate the whole thing, right? And then we'll say like he
can't, you know, he can't, you know, I don't know, you know,
get an עליה, aliyah, he can't be a שליח ציבור, shaliach tzibbur,
he can't count as a מנין—I minyan mean, I—I mentioned all these
things that usually would be only to men anyway, but okay. But
whatever, you know, all these types of ways in which you wind
up like excluding that person, right? So okay. So okay. So now
anyway, what do you see from all this? What you see from
all of this is that we allow when everybody
is—when the brother is a חרש, cheresh, we treat it all as
it's all rabbinic. We're not concerned the case of the brother's a
חרש cheresh will get confused with a ייבום yibbum case when the
brother is a פקח. pike'ach. That was why we brought this in.
Is that clear? We allow all of this to work because it's
all rabbinic, it's all חרש cheresh talking about here. So you see
we're not concerned that a brother חרש cheresh will get confused with
a brother who's a פקח. pike'ach. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
מחוורתא כדשנין מעיקרא. ela michvarta kideshanin me'ikara. It's better like we said
before that the case that's a problem is—is that the case that
the person—a חרש cheresh is married to a woman דאורייתא de'oraita and
can't divorce her is when his—it was ייבום yibbum and his brother
was a פקח. pike'ach. Okay, his brother was a פקח, pike'ach, it
was a ייבום דאורייתא, yibbum de'oraita, he's married to her דאורייתא, de'oraita,
and now he can't divorce her. But if the brother was a
חרש, cheresh, we would allow him to divorce her and we're not
afraid that they'll get confused. Okay, so where are we up to?
What
we're up to is that רב כהנא אמר רב Rav Kahana amar
Rav said if the חרש cheresh can communicate through writing he's not
a חרש, cheresh, it's a form of speaking. We have a ברייתא
braita that established that that's not true. That a חרש cheresh who
was always a חרש, cheresh, everybody would say could not give a
גט get even if he could write. And at most you have
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel saying that if he
was born... A non-חרש cheresh and now he's a חרש cheresh then
his writing can—then his writing can—much smaller—then his writing can redefine him.
Okay now, now the גמרא Gemara is going to pull back to
that. Wait, let's just finish this. אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan,
חלוקין עליו חבריו דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. chalukin alav chaveirav d'Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. Although we implicitly said it before, he's saying it explicitly.
Don't think that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who
says if he can write and he wasn't born a חרש cheresh
it's okay, that he's, that that's assumed by everyone else. That's not
true. He actually is, that's his position, but the others disagree with
him. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami
tanina, נשתתק לא
יוציא נתחרש אמהו nishtatek lo yotzi nitcharesh amhu או נשתתק או נשתתק
לא יוציא עולמית. o nishtatek o nishtatek lo yotzi olamit. If the
woman became a שוטה, shota, he cannot divorce her. Okay, this is
a case of, you know, two people married, the woman became ill
or whatever, they were both פקח, pikeach, they both married דאורייתא, d'Oraita,
then the woman became a שוטה, shota, she's no longer in her
right mind, he's no longer able to divorce her. If he became
a חרש cheresh or he became a שוטה, shota, he can never
divorce her. So here's a case that he married her as a
פקח, pikeach, he became a חרש, cheresh, and it says he can
never divorce her. Even if he becomes a פקח? pikeach? So, well,
no, that's a good point, but no. מאי עולמית? Mai olamit? What
does it mean never? לאו אף על גב דיכול לדבר מתוך הכתב?
Lav af al gav d'yachol l'dabeir mitoch haksav? Presumably it means that
no matter what, even if he can communicate through writing, it doesn't
matter, he's a חרש, cheresh, can't divorce, so you see that the
position that rejects רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, writing
doesn't help, even if he was started life not as a חרש.
cheresh. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, אי לאו דשמעינן מרב יוחנן
ilav dashminan m'Rav Yochanan if רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan had not spelled
that out for us that there's a position that disagrees with רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, הוה אמינא רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל לפרושי טעמא דתנא קמא הוא דאתא, hava amina Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel l'parushei taama d'Tanna Kamma hu d'ata, I would have said רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is just clarifying the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma and everybody agrees that if he starts off not
as a חרש cheresh writing works. ומאי עולמית? U'mai olamit? So what
does this משנה mishna mean when it says he can never divorce
her if he became a חרש? cheresh? It means אף על גב
דחזינא ליה דחריף, af al gav d'chazina lei d'charif, even if we
saw that he was clearly very intelligent, he could never divorce her
unless he can write. You know why? Because if he can write,
he's no longer a חרש. cheresh. Meaning as long as he's a
חרש cheresh and can't communicate, he can never divorce her, no matter
how intelligent he appears. By the way, that's also important, right, that
again shows a formalistic approach. It shows that the person can clearly
be highly intelligent, but if he's not considered to be able to
communicate and he's still a חרש, cheresh, he can never divorce her.
But I would have said as soon as he can write, then
he's no longer חרש, cheresh, then he could divorce her. So if
it wasn't that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan pointed out that there's a
position that rejects רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, I
would have said that this משנה mishna is consistent with רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. And what it means is he
can never divorce her no matter how intelligent he is as long
as he can't speak. But once he can speak, even if speaking
is through writing, I might have said that's okay. So comes along
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and says no, sorry, that's not okay. According
to the other position who argues on רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel, even writing does not constitute speaking, even if he
did not start his life as a חרש. cheresh. אף על גב
דחזינא דחריף. Af al gav d'chazina d'charif. אי נמי לכדרב יצחק, Ee
nami l'cheRav Yitzchak,
or maybe the עולמית olamit is coming to tell us the point
that רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak says. דאמר רב יצחק, D'amar Rav Yitzchak,
דבר תורה שוטה מתגרשת. d'var Torah shota mitgereshes. Torah—biblically speaking a woman
who's a שוטה shota who's not of her right mind can be
divorced. Now you remember there was an earlier discussion on whether a
small child could be divorced. There in order to be divorced, the
woman has to be able to שומרת את גיטה, shomeres es gita,
protect her גט. get. Okay
so and understand that she's divorced and not come back. And understand
that she's divorced and not come back. So there's a certain so
the גמרא Gemara in יבמות Yevamos that discusses this basically assumes that
a שוטה shota is able to be שומרת את גיטה, shomeres es
gita, is able to and therefore דאורייתא d'Oraita she can be divorced.
Okay so מידי דהוה אפקחת בעל כרחה, midi d'hava a'pikeches ba'al korcha,
the same way a woman who's of right mind can be divorced
against her will, so what if the שוטה shota doesn't you know
doesn't under you know isn't willing and participate and doesn't have דעת?
da'as? A woman is divorced against her דעת da'as anyway. Okay but
again, presuming that she can watch her גט get and understand that
she's divorced. Okay so but she is divorced, even though she's not
a בר דעת. bar da'as. ומה טעם אמרו אינה מתגרשת? U'ma taam
amru eina mitgereshes? Here you go Michael once again, Michael has written
the גמרא Gemara already. שלא ינהגו בה מנהג הפקר. shelo yinhagu ba
minhag hefker. They did not let her be divorced so that people
should not take advantage of her. Okay, which by the way is
like a big problem in these homes that they have, you know,
for kids with who you know whatever young adults that the parents
can't watch them anymore or they're actually adults but you know they're
not of of the you know they're not with of sufficient intellectual
capacities that you know even sometimes the people in those in those
facilities take sexual advantage of the people.
So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says so that's why it would
have said עולמית. olamit. To עולמית olamit not to is a way
of saying that when the... man is a פיקח *pikeach* or a
שוטה *shoteh* then it's really דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* he can't divorce her. Right?
It only said עולמית *olamis* by the man. It said if she
becomes a שוטה *shoteh* she can't be divorced, if he becomes a
חרש *cheresh* or שוטה *shoteh* he can never divorce her. So I
would have said the word never to emphasize that for him it's
דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* and for her it's דרבנן *d'Rabbanan*. She דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* really
could be divorced, but Rabbananly she can't. For him, never, meaning not
even even דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* he can't divorce her. Okay, so if it
was just from that משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* that said when a man
becomes a חרש *cheresh* he can never divorce the woman, I would
have said that actually he could divorce her if he's able to
write. But comes along רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* says no actually there are those that argue on רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* and would say that even if
he can write and even if he started not as a חרש
*cheresh*, he remains a חרש *cheresh* and he cannot divorce her. So
as הלכה למעשה *halacha l'maaseh*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ends with two
opinions. According to the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, רב כהנא אמר רב *Rav
Kahana amar Rav* is totally rejected, at least their fundamental position that
if somebody is born a חרש *cheresh*, even if he's intelligent and
can write and communicate, he remains a חרש *cheresh*. And at most
you have the position רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*,
that if somebody is born not a חרש *cheresh*, becomes a חרש
*cheresh* and can communicate through writing, maybe we're prepared to redefine him
according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, but the
חכמים *Chachamim* disagree. So this as I said becomes like a major
challenge because in the last two centuries there's been a lot, 250
years or so, I think schools for the deaf were about 250
years ago, forget when they started anyway, there's been a lot of
halachic reassessment of the category of חרש *cheresh*. All right, so you
have to see those תשובות *teshuvos*, but let's at least acknowledge that
that's the challenge.
It's another שיעור *shiur* for another time. I have to חזור *chazor*
review this. Just as a matter of what do you do with
a minority opinion that is rejected by the סוגיא sugya *sugya*? Well
it's clear that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rejects רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, it just says חולקין עליו חביריו *cholkin alav
chaveirav*. But the original דאמר רב כהנא *d'amar Rav Kahana*. Oh yeah,
yeah. What do you do with it? Like it has no halachic
force? I know, that's the problem. That's how הלכה *halacha* works. If
you have a way of arguing but it doesn't seem like the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is giving any opening to
say that there, which is really what do you do? It's such
a great position that you want to go. A, like I said,
it both logically makes an enormous amount of sense. How could it
be that somebody is so intelligent and so able to clearly communicate,
just logically how could it be that that person halachically is seen
as not a בר דעת bar daas, *bar daas*? We have also
I think we have voice activate, like you could write something into
the computer and it would vocalize that's interesting. Oh, vocalizers. That's interesting.
Stephen Hawking even. Not a חרש *cheresh* though, that's the problem. I
know I'm talking about Hawking, I'm talking about the technology. That's interesting.
You know maybe now even those that were not prepared to go
with this redefinition, maybe there's another basis just to sort of say
that they actually are even speaking, they're creating sounds. That's an interesting
thought. Yeah. I remember mentioned that a חרש *cheresh* could not be
בעל תוקע *baal tokeia*. Right, could not be מוציא *motzi* anybody in
any מצוה *mitzvah*, certainly not a מצוה דאורייתא *mitzvah d'Oraisa*. If they
have Hawking's voice? It doesn't matter. Right, can't do anything that's at
a דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* level. Not a בר דעת *bar daas*, right, exactly.
Interesting that the whole thing is brought about by the abstraction of
the notion like
what we're talking about is writing a גט get *get* again. Right,
that's the real thing. Right. Everybody wrote their own גט get *get*
then you could say we may not even have gotten here. It's
only by abstracting it and bringing in a שליח shaliach, *shaliach* so
that you have to designate someone else to write the גט get
*get* that the חרש *cheresh* became kind of an issue. No but
a חרש *cheresh* but you have to still be a בר דעת
*bar daas*, right? So if somebody
were חרש *cheresh* and did write their own גט get *get*, it
still wouldn't be good, right? Yeah but would we have gotten here?
I don't know I can't answer that question. But the Stephen Hawking
case is not theoretical because he actually did divorce his wife after
he completely lost the ability to speak. But he's not Jewish. Okay,
but differences.
We have to figure that out in דיני בני נח *dinei bnei
Noach*. Yeah. So you mentioned something interesting about getting an עליה *aliyah*,
but I have to ask the question if you can't speak let's
say are you allowed to get an עליה *aliyah* if you can't
make a ברכה *bracha*? Oh yeah that's another interesting question. So actually
I won't give a full answer but I will say there's a
משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* that says חמישה לא יתרומו *chamishah lo yisrumu* and
if אם תרמו תרומתן תרומה *im sarmu trumasan trumah* and one of
them is an אלם *illem*. So why can a person who's mute,
again בר דעת *bar daas*, why can they לכתחילה *l'chatchilah* not take
תרומה *trumah*? The answer is because they can't make a ברכה *bracha*.
So it would be בדיעבד *b'diavad* of course it would work but
it's not a לכתחילה *l'chatchilah* taking because it's not מלווה *melaveh* with
a ברכה *bracha*. So in particular actually by עליה *aliyah* where part
of the whole טקס *tekes* is like the making of the ברכה
*bracha*, you know. So yeah that's a separate issue which is a
good one, yes. Is there any interesting connection with the סין *sin*
and the שין *shin* of שוטה *shoteh* and סוטה *sotah*? Oh that's
a good question. I don't know I'm not an
etymologist, anyway that I can answer that question but I will tell
you that רמב"ם *Rambam* he has הלכות סוטה *Hilchos Sotah*, you know
in the רמב"ם *Rambam* one of his
one of his הלכות *halachos* in
נשים *Nashim* is סוטה *Sotah*, but apparently when it... But then for
now in current רמב"ם they write it with a סמך. samech. Anyway,
okay let's take a look at the משנה. Mishna. אמרו לו נכתוב
גט לאשתך, Amru lo nichtov get le-ishtacha,
ואמר להן, ve-amar la-hen, says now back to a normal בר דעת,
okay.
And they say to a guy, סתם, stam, "Hey, should we write
a גט to your wife?" Like they, they suggest it, maybe you're
going to die soon, you're going off on a trip. Would you
like us to write a גט to your wife? Again, if somebody's
dying he wants a גט to be written to his wife so
she doesn't have to worry about יבום. yibum. יבום's Yibum always in
the background. Okay, ואמר להן כתבו, ve-amar la-hen ktovu, write it.
אמרו לסופר, Amru le-sofer, so they went and they told a סופר,
sofer, וכתב, ve-chtav, and the סופר sofer wrote it, ולעדים וחתמו, ve-le-edim
ve-chasmu, and they told the witnesses and they signed it. אף על
פי שכתבו וחתמו ונתנו לו, Af al pi she-kasvu ve-chasmu ve-nasnu lo,
so they wrote it and they signed it and they gave it
to him, וחזר ונתנו לה, ve-chazar ve-nasnu lah, he himself gave it
to the wife because he only said write it, he didn't say
give it, so he himself gave it to the wife. הרי הגט
בטל, Harei ha-get batel, it's invalid. עד שיאמר לסופר כתוב ולעדים חתומו.
Ad she-yomar le-sofer ktov ve-le-edim chasomu. You know why it's invalid? Because
he did not directly instruct the סופר sofer and the witnesses. Okay,
he said to them write it and they told the סופר sofer
and the עדים, edim, and he has to tell them directly. So
you might remember this, the issue about מילי נמסרן לשליח. mili nimseran
le-shaliach. If you tell a שליח, does the סופר sofer have to
hear it directly from the husband or not? Which is what the
גמרא Gemara. says. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara טעימא
דלא אמר תנו. Taima de-lo amar tenu. גמרא Gemara says
the reason it understands that there was a problem here was they
only said to these witnesses write it. So remember if you remember
the earlier משנה, Mishna write might suggest you have to do it
yourself, תנו tenu is giving them a little more latitude, see that
it gets given. So the problem is that he
didn't say תנו. tenu. הא אמר תנו, Ha amar tenu, if he
had said תנו, tenu, so basically that would have given them more
latitude. In that case, נותנים, notnim, maybe they could have, they could
give it and have somebody else write it. So מני, mani, who
would that be going like? רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, דאמר מילי נמסרן
לשליח. de-amar mili nimseran le-shaliach. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who says that
under certain cases, at least cases of תנו, tenu, if it's a
בית דין, beis din, not תנו tenu if it's only two, we'll
see about the בית דין beis din again in a minute, but
if you have three people and you say תנו, tenu, then you've
empowered them, you know, you've given them the latitude and then they
can go ahead and give it to somebody else. It's words, it's
only a verbal appointment, there's no גט that they're holding, but they
can pass on that verbal appointment to somebody else. That was רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, you might remember, if you say תנו tenu to
three people, he said they can have other people write it. Okay,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of this משנה.
Mishna.
Now by the way, I want to point you to רש"י. Rashi.
If you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says about
five lines after the רש"י Rashi in the גמרא Gemara, begins, the
lines start with אפילו רבי מאיר. afilu Rebbi Meir. רש"י Rashi says,
you see the words אפילו רבי מאיר afilu Rebbi Meir at the
beginning of a line in רש"י Rashi about eight lines before the
lines get medium-sized in רש"י. Rashi. אפילו רבי מאיר מודה, afilu Rebbi
Meir modeh, רש"י Rashi says לקמן בפרק החציץ קביי. le-kaman be-perek hatzis
kavei. "If he said write, etc., it's no good." So רש"י Rashi
had our sixth פרק, perek, we already learned that משנה Mishna about
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi and the three
בית דין. beis din. רש"י Rashi had that as a switched order
of the seventh and the sixth פרק perek than we do. Okay,
so all the way to רש"י Rashi here are constantly referring to
a סוגיא we've already done, and רש"י Rashi is constantly saying like
we're going to do in the next פרק. perek. Okay, so that's
interesting. In some מסכתות masechtos there's a question which order the פרקים
prokim come in. Anyway, back to the גמרא. Okay, אימא סיפא, eima
seifa, let's look at the end of the משנה. עד שיאמר לסופר
כתוב ולעדים חתומו. Ad she-yomar le-sofer ktov ve-le-edim chasomu. It sounds like
there's no way it can work. תנו, Tenu, בית דין, beis din,
nothing works unless you tell the סופר sofer directly. You need a
direct verbal instruction to the סופר sofer and to the witnesses. So
the גמרא says אתיא כרבי יוסי, atya ke-Rebbi Yosi, that's going like
רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, דאמר מילי לא נמסרן לשליח, de-amar mili lo
nimseran le-shaliach, that says verbal appointment can never be given over, can
never be passed on. Okay, even תנו, tenu, even בית דין, beis
din, you always need direct sort of instruction from the husband. So
רישא רבי מאיר וסיפא רבי יוסי? reisha Rebbi Meir ve-seifa Rebbi Yosi?
The רישא reisha sounds like you have some latitude, it's only because
you said כתבו, ktovu, that's going like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. The
end sounds like רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, that nothing will ever work
except the direct instruction. So the גמרא says is that possible? אין,
רישא רבי מאיר וסיפא רבי יוסי. In, reisha Rebbi Meir ve-seifa Rebbi
Yosi. Yeah, fine. Okay, the beginning gives you some latitude, if you
said תנו tenu maybe it would be good, the סיפא seifa goes
like רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi and you have no latitude. אביי אמר
Abaye amar no, כולה רבי מאיר היא, kula Rebbi Meir hi, it's
all רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. That if you did say תנו tenu
and it was a בית דין, beis din, you're okay. והכא במאי
עסקינן דלא אמר תנו. Ve-hacha be-mai askinan de-lo amar tenu. What the
משנה is talking about is in a context where you did not
say תנו, tenu, that you're only saying כתבו, ktovu, then you have
to speak directly to the סופר. sofer. If you want to say
תנו, tenu, you have more, you don't have to be direct. But
if you're going to say כתבו, ktovu, you have to directly instruct
the סופר. sofer. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, if that's
true, עד שיאמר תנו מיבעי ליה. ad she-yomar tenu mibaye lei. Then
it shouldn't have said it's never good until you directly instruct the
סופר. sofer. The easier thing to be would say it's not good
unless you say תנו. tenu. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן דלא אמר תנו.
Ela hacha be-mai askinan de-lo amar tenu.
Fine.
Let's say it this way. The משנה *mishna* is talking in a
context that there's only two of them. So if there's only two
of them, it's never good unless you instruct them directly. Remember, according
to Rabbi Meir, it's only they can only pass it on if
there are three and you said תנו *tnu*. So why does the
משנה *mishna* sound like you have no options other than instructing them
directly? Because we're dealing that you only said to two people. Okay.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says no. אי הכי *i
hachi* says the גמרא *Gemara*, and the גמרא *Gemara* still isn't satisfied.
עד שיאמר שלשה מיבעי ליה *ad sheyomar shlosha mibaye lei*. Don't tell
me you need to directly instruct them. You should tell me the
other options. You can say תנו *tnu* as long as it's a
בית דין *beis din*. I'm sorry, says the גמרא *Gemara*, it doesn't
sound like that. It sounds like you have absolutely no option. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says אלא *ella* fine, we'll go the other way,
which is clearly the easier way to read it. כרבי יוסי היא
*KeRabbi Yosi hi*. Okay? והכא *ve hacha* so now why does the
beginning sound like if you said תנו *tnu* it might have been
okay? והכא במאי עסקינן *ve hacha bemai askinan* what are we talking
about? דלא אמר אמרו *de lo amar imru*. No, because what the
beginning means is if you said כתבו *kisvu* it's no good, maybe
there is an option that it could work according to רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi*. What's the option? That you directly told them to tell
someone else. Remember the גמרא *Gemara* just discussed that before whether according
to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* if you explicitly told them to tell
someone else would that work? אי הכי *i hachi* says the גמרא
*Gemara*, עד שיאמר אמרו מיבעי ליה *ad sheyomar imru mibaye lei*. Still
not happy. No. I'm sorry, the end of the משנה *mishna* sounds
like no options. So according to you, it should have said you
have an option to tell them to tell someone else. ועוד מי
מודה רבי יוסי באומר אמרו *ve od mi modei Rabbi Yosi be
omer imru*? Since when does רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* agree to that?
דתנן *de tnan* and now we get to this whole כתב סופר
*ksav sofer* and חתם סופר *chasam sofer*. Let's just try to read
this. כתב סופר ועד כשר *ksav sofer ve ed kasher*. If you
have the handwriting of the סופר *sofer* and one witness it's good.
ואמר רבי ירמיה חתם סופר שנינו *ve amar Rabbi Yirmiyah chasam sofer
shaninu*. No, it means the סופר *sofer*'s signature. Now why is a
סופר *sofer*'s signature good? Because we should be afraid as you'll see
that the husband didn't say that and they got the the סופר
*sofer* to sign because they were embarrassed. ואמר רב חסדא מתניתין מני
רבי יוסי היא דאמר מילי לא מימסרן לשליח *ve amar Rav Chisda
masnisin mani Rabbi Yosi hi damar mili lo mimseran leshliach*. Our משנה
*mishna* is רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* that says that the words aren't
given over, so we're not afraid that the סופר *sofer* signed because
the messengers were embarrassed and had him sign even though he had
not been appointed. You know why we don't have to be afraid
of that? Because it's רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* that you have to
hear directly from the husband. Okay, so that's why it's okay that
the סופר *sofer* signed and we don't have to be afraid that
he wasn't really appointed by the husband to do so. But the
גמרא *Gemara* says, ואי סלקא דעתך מודה רבי יוסי באומר אמרו *ve
isalka daitach modei Rabbi Yosi be omer imru*, but if רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi* would allow for a case of not directly hearing from
the husband of telling witnesses to tell the סופר *sofer*, so נפקא
מינה חורבא *nafka mina churba*, the destruction will come out, this case
is still a problem. דזימנין דאמר להו לשנים אמרו לסופר ויכתוב ולפלוני
ופלוני ויחתמו *de zimnin de amar lehu lishnayim imru lesofer veyichtov uleploni
ploni veyachtmu*, the husband will tell people tell the סופר *sofer* to
write and tell Reuven and Shimon to sign, and it's that you
don't have to directly instruct them because it's אומר אמרו *omer imru*,
ומשום כיסופא דסופר *ve mishum kissufa desofer* and because they'll be embarrassed,
they're concerned for the embarrassment of the סופר *sofer*, קא חשיב ליה
*ka chashiv lei*, they'll have the סופר *sofer* be one of the
signatures, ובעל לא אמר הכי *u baal lo amar hachi* and the
husband didn't say this. So I went through that quickly because we
had done it before. But the basic point is is that רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* says אומר אמרו *omer imru* is no good. You
know how I know רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* knows אומר אמרו *omer
imru* is no good? At least according to רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah*,
חתם סופר *chasam sofer* works. And the only reason the signature of
the סופר *sofer* works and we're not afraid that that that the
messengers told him to do it because they were afraid that he
might be embarrassed and that the husband had not said it is
because we're going like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*. And according to רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*, everybody has to hear straight from the husband. Which
shows that for רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* there's no אומר אמרו *omer
imru*. There's no way you can do it without having heard straight
from the husband. Okay? So we're back to our problem which is
the beginning sounds like it's only because of כתבו *kisvu*, sounds like
there are some options that it might work, and the end sounds
like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* that there are no options, that you
have to hear straight from the husband, there are no alternatives. So
we will leave this for tomorrow and find out how the גמרא
*Gemara* resolves the רישא *reisha* and the סיפא *seifa*. All right.